<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>DSCI_542_blog</title>
<link>https://dsci_542_blog_hhkwok/</link>
<atom:link href="https://dsci_542_blog_hhkwok/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog built with Quarto</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Post With Code</title>
  <dc:creator>Harlow Malloc</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dsci_542_blog_hhkwok/posts/post-with-code/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is a post with executable code.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>code</category>
  <category>analysis</category>
  <guid>https://dsci_542_blog_hhkwok/posts/post-with-code/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://dsci_542_blog_hhkwok/posts/post-with-code/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab2</title>
  <dc:creator>Hugo Kwok</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dsci_542_blog_hhkwok/posts/lab2/lab2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="the-battery-saver-mode-how-napping-affect-work-efficiency" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-battery-saver-mode-how-napping-affect-work-efficiency">The Battery Saver Mode: How Napping Affect Work Efficiency</h2>
<p>Hello everyone and welcome to my first data science blog. Today I want to talk about a problem that every student and worker face every day. That is the feeling of being very tired after lunch. In Hong Kong we call this “food coma”. It is a very terrible feeling. You sit in front of the computer but your brain is not moving. It is exactly like using your smartphone to play heavy games in the morning. By 2 pm the battery drop to 20 percent and the phone turn into red color mode. You start to worry if the phone can last until you go back home.</p>
<p>Our brain is actually the same concept as the phone battery. After we work for the whole morning our energy level go down very fast. When the energy is low we become very slow in reaction and we make careless mistake easily. Some people suggest we should drink coffee but some people suggest we should take a nap. Taking a nap is like plugging the phone to a portable charger for a quick charge. But does this really works or not? Or is it just wasting time? As a data science student I want to find out the truth using data instead of just guessing. In this blog I analyze a dataset to see if “charging” our body in afternoon really help us work better.</p>
<section id="why-efficiency-is-important" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-efficiency-is-important">Why Efficiency is Important</h3>
<p>I choose this topic because I am a student in the Master of Data Science program now. The workload is very heavy. We have many labs and quizzes every week. In Hong Kong I used to work in an office and the working hour is very long. Sometimes we work until 9 pm. But studying here is even more stressful. Every day I wake up early and study until late night. I always feel that I do not have enough time.</p>
<p>Because I do not have enough time, efficiency is the most important thing for me. If I can finish a lab in 2 hours instead of 4 hours, I can have more time to sleep. So I am always looking for method to work faster. I notice that around 3 pm I am very useless. I stare at the code but I cannot find the bug. But if I close my eyes for a short time maybe I can fix the bug in 5 minutes. I want to prove this feeling with numbers. I want to know if I should feel guilty when I sleep in the library or if I am actually doing the right thing for my work.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-data-source" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-data-source">The Data Source</h3>
<p>For this project I search on the internet and I use a dataset from Kaggle. Kaggle is a very famous website for data scientist to find data. The dataset I found record the sleep habit and productivity score of many office workers. You can imagine this data is the battery usage log from different smartphones.</p>
<p>The dataset contains many columns. It has the age of the worker, how many hours they sleep at night, and do they take a nap during the day. It also has a column called “efficiency_score”. This score is a number from 0 to 10. If the number is high it means the worker finish many tasks. If the number is low it means they are slow.</p>
<p>Before I start the analysis I need to clean the data. Real world data is always messy like the cable tangled in your bag. Some rows have missing value. For example some worker did not write down their age. I use Python to remove these empty rows to make sure my analysis is accurate. I also check if there is any strange number, like if someone say they sleep 25 hours a day which is impossible. After cleaning the data I am ready to check the result.</p>
</section>
<section id="exploratory-data-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exploratory-data-analysis">Exploratory Data Analysis</h3>
<p>First I did some exploratory data analysis to look at the general picture. In data science we call this EDA. This step is to just look at the data without complex math. I calculate the average productivity score for two groups of people. The first group is the people who take a nap. I call them the “Charger Group”. The second group is people who do not nap. I call them the “Low Battery Group”. The result is very interesting. The computer output show that the Charger Group has a average score of 7.8 out of 10. The Low Battery Group only has a average score of 6.5 out of 10.</p>
<p>We can see there is a difference. This is very similar to the fast charging function on new phones. You do not need to charge it to 100 percent to see the benefit. Just a quick 20 mins charge can give battery enough power to run heavy apps for few more hours. The data suggest that people who do not nap tend to have drop in performance late in the day. This is similar to a phone that go into low power mode. When the phone is in low power mode, it start lagging when you open apps. Humans are the same. When we are tired we read one sentence three times and still do not understand.</p>
<p>Statistical Testing</p>
<p>However just looking at the average number is not enough. My professor always say that looking at the mean is dangerous because sometimes result happen by luck. Maybe the people in the napping group are just smarter people? We do not know.</p>
<p>To be more sure I perform a statistical test called the t test. In our lab we learn that t test compare two groups to see if they are truly different. This is like checking if one brand of charger is really better than another brand or if the difference is just random error.</p>
<p>I state my hypothesis. The Null Hypothesis is that napping make no difference. The Alternative Hypothesis is that napping change the efficiency. I run the code in Python and I get a p value. The p value is 0.03.</p>
<p>In data science usually we use 0.05 as a cut off line. If the p value is smaller than 0.05 it means the result is significant. Since 0.03 is smaller than 0.05 we can say the result is real. It confirm that the difference in efficiency is likely not a coincidence. So the charging action really change the hardware performance of our body. It seems that giving our brain a short break allow it to clear the memory and run faster when we wake up.</p>
</section>
<section id="limitations-of-the-project" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="limitations-of-the-project">Limitations of the Project</h3>
<p>Although the result look very good I need to be honest about the limitation. As a data scientist we need to think critically. The data I use is “self reported”. This means the workers write down the score by themselves.</p>
<p>Sometimes people lie. Maybe a worker is very lazy but he write down a high score because he is afraid the boss will see it. Also maybe the people who take naps are the people who have easier jobs. If the job is easy maybe they have less stress and can work better. The data does not tell us what kind of job they are doing. This is a missing variable.</p>
<p>Also the dataset does not say how long they nap. It just says “Nap: Yes or No”. If someone nap for 3 hours that is too long. If someone nap for 5 minutes that is too short. In the future if I have more time I want to find a better dataset that record the exact minutes of sleeping time. This will help me give better advice.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>In conclusion the data analysis support the idea that napping can improve work efficiency. The statistics show that staffs who take short break to sleep perform better than those who try to work with fatigue. The t test prove that this is statistically significant.</p>
<p>So next time you feel your battery level turning red in afternoon do not feel guilty about taking a nap. It is not being lazy. It is a necessary maintenance step to recharge your system so you can run at full speed again.</p>
<p>However I want to give one warning. Do not charge for too long. If you sleep for more than 30 minutes you might enter deep sleep mode. When you wake up from deep sleep you will feel even more tired and headache. This is like overcharging a battery and making it hot. The best length is around 20 minutes. A quick power nap is the best way to keep your operating system running smooth until the end of work day. I hope this blog help you understand why rest is important. Thank you for reading.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://dsci_542_blog_hhkwok/posts/lab2/lab2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
